Guide to the George R. Miner, Jr. Rice University memorabilia collection, 1926-2002 UA 360
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
George R. Miner, Jr. Rice memorabilia collection
1926-2002
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Miner, George R., 1925-2002
UA 360
5 Linear Feet 9 boxes
The George R. Miner, Jr. Rice memorabilia collection focuses on Rice University athletics. It contains mostly photographs of athletes, coaches, along with action shots of various sports, the majority concerning football. There are also photographs and memorabilia of team reunions, the Rice Athletic Hall of Fame, and Rice alumni events.
Biographical / Historical
George Rufus Miner, Jr. was born in Dallas on Dec. 31, 1926, and grew up in Lake Charles, Louisiana, interrupting his college career to serve in the navy for two years before graduating from Rice Institute in 1950. He majored in mechanical engineering and was a varsity football player. Married to Elaine Dederick (1930-2007) for fifty-two years, he had six children. After graduation, Miner joined his father-in-law's Hosuton-based construction company, becoming president and owner in 1955 and later changed the firm's name to Miner-Dederick. The company was involved in the construction of a number of Houston landmarks and several campus buildings. For decades, Miner was deeply involved in fund raising and alumni affairs. He served two years on the board of governors, was president of the alumni association, endowed several scholarships, was inducted into the Athletic Hall of Fame, was named an outstanding engineering alumnus, and in 1995 won the gold medal for his many contributions to the university. He died on Feb. 28, 2002, in Houston, and is buried in Forest Park Lawndale Cemetery.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes notebooks from Miner's undergraduate classes; photographs of Rice athletes and coaches; football ephemera; objects and apparel from his football career and fund-raising achievements.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges; College students -- Texas; Football; Sports
Document Types
memorabilia; notes; photographs
Subjects (Persons)
Miner, George R., 1925-2002
Subjects (Corporations)
Rice University
- Series I: Class Notebooks and quizzes
  - Biology 100 (2 volumes) (Box 1)
  - Civil Engineering 300 (2 volumes) (Box 1)
  - Engineering 110 (Box 1)
  - Engineering 250a (surveying) [see Rice History Corner, June 23, 2015] (Box 1)
  - Engineering 260 (Box 1)
  - Engineering 270 (Box 1)
  - Math 200 (2 volumes) (Box 1)
  - Math 230 (Box 1)
  - Math 300 (Box 1)
  - Mechanical Engineering 300 ( 2 volumes) (Box 2)
  - Mechanical Engineering 310 (Box 2)
  - Mechanical Engineering 410 (Box 2)
  - Mechanical Engineering 420 (2 volumes) (Box 2)
  - Mechanical Engineering 440 (Box 2)
  - Physics 100 (Box 2)
  - Physics 200 (Box 2)
  - Spanish (with Civil Engineering 300) (Box 1)
- Series II: Objects and Apparel
  - Plaque of Coach & Athlete magazine cover, Dec. 1960: "Jess Neely and the King Brothers" (Box 3)
  - Wooden plaque [see Rice History Corner, June 1, 2015] (Box 3)
  - Rice Owls Southwest Conference 1949 football-shaped bank (Box 4)
  - Owl Club plaque: George R. Miner for outstanding support of Rice athletics (Box 4)
  - Association of Rice Alumni president gavel & stand, 1992-1993 (Box 4)
  - Piece of gymnasium composition flooring (Box 4)
  - VHS tape of Rice vs. Texas, 1994-10 (Box 4)
  - Basketballs/football necklace; charms-medals acquired by George Miner [possibly high school] (Box 4)
  - Rice football charms on chain --Orange Bowl 1947, Southwest Conference co-champions 1946 (Box 4)
  - Rice Institute 1950 commencement invitation (Box 4)
  - Programs: Martel College dedication, Rice Associates dinner (Box 4)
  - Rice necktie (Box 5)
  - Rice letter sweater 'R' (Box 5)
  - RIce practice jersey 'Rice AA' (Box 5)
- Series III: Photographs
  - George Miner 1944, 1986 [see Rice History Corner, June 1, 2015] (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Football players, identified
    - Raymond "Dale" Callihan '65 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Richard Chapman '54 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Larry Davis '70 (2) (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Paul Giroski '51 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Vernon Glass '51 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - John Hudson '54 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Robert Johnson '61 with Barney Kessler (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Ervin Kalb '16 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - John Kelly Sr. '50 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Alfred "Ike" Neumann '51 (2) (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Don Rhoden '53 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Frank Ryan '58 (2) (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Jim Vining '66 (2) (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Malcolm Walker '65 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Joe Watson '50 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Football players, unidentified (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Football action shots
    - General (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
    - Rice 14, Texas 7, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Rice 13, TCU 0, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Rice 6, TCU 0, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Rice v. Baylor, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Football team
    - 1941 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - 1944 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - 1946; 1986- 40th reunion (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - 1947 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - 1949 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Football coaches
    - Staff
      - Red Bale, Bob Bossons, Joe Davis, Bo Hagan, Charlie Moore, Jess Neely, Eddie Wojecki, 3 unidentified, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 16)
      - Red Bale, Bartosh, Bob Bossons, Bo Hagan, Hess, Nick Lanza, Mayo, Charlie Moore, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Jess Neely (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Red Bale retirement celebration? (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Cohen House remodel (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Reckling Field (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Jamail Plaza (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Shepherd School of Music (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Will Rice College (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - John Miner (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Oversize
    - Action shots: Sam Mays '36, Harry Witt '36, John Sylvester '36, Bill Wallace (Box 7)
    - Team photos: late 1940s outside Rice fieldhouse; 1947 Orange Bowl team (Box 7)
    - Football players: Bill McClanahan cartoon collages of Johnny Burrell 1961, and Frank Ryan/King Hill 1957? (Box 7)
    - All-America college team, Hamilton Nichols, 1944 (Box 7)
    - At Ye Olde College Inn: Joe Davis, Charlie Moore, Cecil Grigg, Ernie Coker, Jess Neely, Don Suman, A.M. Bale (Box 7)
- Series IV: Sports ephemera
  - Football
    - George Miner varsity certificate, 1944-1946 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - General (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Hall of Fame football inductees [photo]: William Henry '45, Weldon Humble '47, Froggy Williams '50, Alan Chapman, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Other sports
    - Athletes and coaches, identified
      - Claude Bracey '30 (2) (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - George Carlisle (with Bob Hope) (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Julian Dormant '19 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - John Frankie (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Fred Hansen '63 (2) (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Jack Patterson '39 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Walter E. Red '65 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Harold Solomon '74 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Dale W. Spence '56 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Don Suman (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - John "Buddy" Weaver '50 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Joe Williams '67 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Athletes and coaches, unidentified (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Cross-country team: B.B. Arnold, Emmett Brunson, Fay Hilliard, Russell Lee Jacobe, Sol Kaplan, Jesse M. Willis, James Wilmouth, Jack Yarbrough, 1928 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Basketball teams, 1944-1945 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Basketball players and coach: George Calisle, Larry Phillips, Kendall Rhine, Herb Steinkamp, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Series V: Honors
  - "An Evening for Rice's Honor" [Miner as honoree], 1986-09-04 (Box 9)
  - Houston Chronicle article, 1986-09-14 (Box 9)
  - "An Evening for Rice's Honor" photo album, 1986-09-04 (Box 9)
  - Replica of William M. Rice statue: Mr. & Mrs. George R. Miner, Jr., Founder's Club 1972-73 (Box 9)